Finding Aid for the Kumez Hachimonji papers, 1918-1955 LSC.2010.10
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kumezo Hachimonji papers
1918-1955
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hachimonji, Kumezo
LSC.2010.10
1 oversize_boxes
Kumezo Hachimonji was born in 1888. A native of Miyagi Prefecture, he graduated from Thoku Gakuin in Sendai and arrived in the United States in 1918. He received his BS from Columbia University. Before World War II he owned and operated Valley Seed Company in El Monte, California. He was also known as K. Hatchmonji. The collection consists of diaries, essays, memoirs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, and photographic negatives related to the life of agricultural specialist and merchant Kumezo Hachimonji. Materials in the collection are in English and Japanese.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942331033606533
Biography
Hachimonji was born in 1888; a native of Miyagi Prefecture, he graduated from Thoku Gakuin in Sendai and arrived in the United States in 1918; BS, Columbia University; owned and operated Valley Seed Company in El Monte, California, before World War II; he was also known as K. Hatchmonji; died in 1956.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of diaries, essays, memoirs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, and photographic negatives related to the life of agricultural specialist and merchant Kumezo Hachimonji. Correspondence is made up of typewritten excerpts from internment camp letters exchanged between the Hachimonjis and their friends. Hachimonji's memoirs are contained in a volume which spans the dates 1934-39. The essays in the collection, put together around 1955, cover a variety of topics, including the Arab-Israeli conflict, farming, wartime evacuation, Japanese-Chinese relations, racism, and immigration. A scrapbook contains articles by Hachimonji on agriculture which appeared in a Japanese language newspaper, 1939-40.
Materials in the collection are in English and Japanese.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Memoirs and essays.
Diaries, 1941 and 1945-46.
Four scrapbooks.
Two photographic negatives of Hachimonji's wedding.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Special Collections.
Japanese Americans -- United States -- Archives.; Merchants -- California -- El Monte -- Archives.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Scrapbooks.; Hachimonji, Kumezo, 1888-1956--Archives.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles)
- Hachimonji papers, 1918-1955; 1.5 linear ft.
  - Memoirs, To my children, 2 volumes., 1934-1939 & 1955; (2 diary-books) (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Volume 1., 1934-1939 (Box 61, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      He wrote: "I have [for] a long time been thinking of writing down memoirs of such nature that relates to our boys' life, Memoirs that would interest them when they are grown, that would help them in steering through the life when they are grown. I would write my failures -- try avoid[ing] them, my boys."
    - Volume 2., 1955 (Box 61, Folder 1)
      A collection of essays on a wide variety of topics -- Arab-Israel conflict, farming, wartime evacuation, religion, Japanese-Chinese relations, racism, and immigration, etc. -- which were written after he became ill.
  - Diaries, 2 volumes., 1941 & 1945-1946; (2 diary-books) (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook I, The Dawn of Life., 1928-1945; (1 oversize scrapbook) (Box 308)
    Contains records, documents and photographs on his children with explanatory notes.
  - Scrapbook II, The Long Journey., 1942-1948; (1 oversize scrapbook) (Box 308)
    Contains typewritten excerpts from the internment camp correspondence exchanged between Hachimonji Kumazo and his children and friends.
  - Scrapbook III., 1918 1924; (1 scrapbook) (Box 61, Folder 3)
    Unindentified newspaper clippings, mostly from English language press.
  - Scrapbook IV., 1939-ca. 1941; (1 scrapbook) (Box 61, Folder 3)
    Clippings of Hachimonji's articles on agriculture which appeared on a Japanese language press (not identified).
  - Two photographic negatives of Hachimonji's wedding., n.d.; (2 items) (Box 61, Folder 4)